Hi, in a previous video, I did a little
soldering iron shootout of sorts between
this new model Weller WE1010
and the venerable Hakko FX 888D and both
of these irons are like $100
class irons. And I came to the
conclusion that they're, you know,
six of one, half dozen the other.
You know, there's not really a huge
amount of difference between them. And
Louis Rossmann,
fellow video blogger, you should uh
subscribe to his channel if you haven't
seen it. It's excellent. He does repair
videos and other advice and stuff. And
he basically did a response video to
this saying, "Well, these are old
technology and he doesn't know why
they're still on sale and you basically
kind of paraphrasing. You can go watch
the video linked it in down below for
yourself. They're basically pretty crap
and you shouldn't buy them. His advice
was he would rather have a new
technology soldering iron even if it's a
rip-off one. In his particular example,
he was referring to basically the the
sort of more professional upgrade to the
Hakko 888D here. And that was the FX
951.
And that FX 951, very good iron of
course, very capable and it does use the
new technology as we'll talk about. But
it's like a $250 plus dollar class iron.
So, you know, a completely different
price bracket to these older technology
irons so to speak. But you can actually
buy
rip-off, you know, clones on eBay or
Alibaba or wherever of that Hakko FX
951 and they're about the same price as
these. So, about, you know, 100 odd US
dollars or something like that. So,
Louis's argument is that he would rather
have one of the new technology irons
even if it's a rip-off compared to a
genuine
one of these, like using the older
technology for the same price. And
it's an interesting argument. I
recommend you watch his video down
below. So, this video is going to kind
of be a response to that response, I
guess, but it's a stand-alone video,
basically looking at the difference
between an old technology iron, like the
FX-888D or the Weller here, and a new
technology iron, this JBC 2B
2B series iron. But, this is a very
expensive iron. I think it's like $500
or something like that. Now, when we're
talking about the difference between old
and new technology, I'm using the quote
marks. Even though it's, you know, it's
technically correct, the difference is
not so much in the station itself or
even the power available in the station.
Like, this is a
65-W capable iron. I believe the JBC
like 130-W
peak
power. So, it's more powerful, but
that's not really what we're talking
about here. The difference is in the the
tips are the same, uh basically, but the
way it actually transfers the heat to
these tips and measures it. Yes, they
are turned off.
Otherwise, I'd be smelling something
quite bad. So, first of all, let's look
at the old-style
soldering iron technology, which has
been around from day dot, and you can
still buy it. And in my opinion, they
are still very useful irons. As we'll
get into, we'll do some demonstrations
later. But, if you take off the sleeve
here, you can see that there is a
ceramic heater element in here like
this. And in terms of the Hakko, I don't
actually know where the actual
temperature sensor itself is. It may
actually be embedded in the ceramic
element or whatever. But, basically,
these old technology ones, the tip is
just that. It is just the tip. Now, you
can get poorly designed tips, you can
get really well designed tips, and there
will be thermal performance differences
between them and between manufacturers,
but the point is is that they're
basically the tip is decoupled from
physically separate from the heating
element and the temperature sensor. So,
you basically got extra thermal
resistance in there because you've got
to rely on the contact and maybe some
air cuz that's a little bit
loosey-goosey, So, there's not as good a
contact between the element itself. So,
when the element heats up, there's going
to be some lag between that element
heating up and the tip actually getting
hot. And well, that's not a great thing
when you're soldering because when you
apply your solder down onto the copper,
and you know, if you've got a large heat
sink you're doing a large ground plane
or a large thermal mass like that, then
it can suck away a lot of the heat. And
all soldering irons, regardless of
whether they're new or old technology,
will actually have a drop in
temperature, and I'll explain that in a
minute. But these newer technology
irons, not just this JBC, but the Hakko
FX 951 and all of the other high-end
ones, basically use a different system.
The tip is not just the tip anymore. The
tip actually contains the heating
element itself up there in there
somewhere. I don't know if I can find
like a cutaway drawing or something,
I'll find one, but the element will be
integrated into the tip as well as the
temperature sensor. And the way you can
tell is cuz look, it's got electrical
contacts on here. And sure enough, you
can actually measure that. There we go.
There's like presumably the coil
resistance. I don't know which way
around the contacts go and which one's
the
thermocouple element and all that, but
basically the element and the
thermocouple are built into the tip.
Now, you don't really have to be a, you
know,
thermal expert to understand that this
is going to be a more responsive
technology. When you apply power to that
heating element, the the tip is going to
heat up quicker and faster, assuming all
things are equal, equal amount of power,
equal amount of element, and everything
else, because there is direct coupling
inside here. They've specifically
engineered and designed and made these
so that they have better thermal
performance than just a, you know, the
ceramic heating element and, well, heat
will get through to the tip eventually,
kind of thing. So, they're the two
differences between the old and the new
technology, and there is absolutely no
doubt at all that the new technology is
better. If you can afford it, get an
integrated element tip soldering iron
like this one, for want of a better
word. I don't know. That'll do. But, are
these old-style ones, you know, I don't
know the exact terms that Louis used,
but he basically said, you know, they're
they're hopeless, right? Don't just
don't buy them. You're better off buying
a clone version of one of these, even if
it's, you know, real crap quality.
You're better off doing this. And, well,
there's some merit in his argument,
because, of course, Louis
does mostly, you know, he's a
professional repair tech. So, he repairs
motherboards and and all sorts of other,
you know, consumer electronics that have
very large ground planes on them and
lots of very delicate surface mount
stuff on those ground planes and things
like that. So, you know, if you're doing
professional electronics repair and
maybe assembly work like that, get one
of these. If you can afford it, get a
direct heat iron. So, there's absolutely
no argument there. But, really, the
question for this video is that are
these old-style ones any good? Are they
still useful? And I reckon the answer is
yes, and I'll demonstrate it. You can
still do an
awful lot, if not most of
the stuff you can do with an old older
style iron like this. Personally, I'm
going to be using my JBC in the lab here
if I have a choice cuz yes, it is better
performance as you will see. All right,
so let's see one of the advantages of
these direct heat irons, but bear in
mind this one is 130 watts peak compared
to 65 watt iron here. But if we switch
them on, then we'll actually be able to
see how quickly they heat up. And this
one well, actually, sorry. That's
That's wrong. Got to wait for this thing
to power up, right? Anyway, well, it's
basically there. The The thing with this
one it has like an auto sleep mode, so
it actually sleeps when you put it into
the stand like this and the actual
temperature is 225. It's actually
dropping, but when you pick it up, it
can actually heat up within I believe
the spec for this is three seconds or
two two seconds or something like that.
Two or three seconds very typical to
have these heat up. So you can actually
have an auto detect stand like this and
which cools the iron down and as soon as
you pick it up, it boom. See how it's
got power on the screen that shows the
amount of power that it's actually
driving into this and if we put it on
here, we can actually see that power bar
go up, right? It's now delivering 100%
power like that and it's and it's
dropping. You'll notice that this is
well, look at that. 120. This one goes
right down. Whereas of course, you've
seen this in the previous video, these
more traditional ones, they take a long
time to heat up. That's going to take
quite a while to get to 260, so you
wouldn't have a like a set back mode for
you know, one of these more traditional
irons cuz it just takes too long to
actually heat these things up. But these
aren't magic of course, they're going to
drop. If you actually look at the specs
for this JBC iron, it says it drops
typically 35°
C temperature tip temperature. And it
says while competing irons, I guess
they're referring to these old
technology ones here, the non-direct
heat type, then they can be up to 70° C
temperature drop. But let's actually do
the sponge test. I've set this to 260.
You can see there's a little bit of
overshoot there. And we're back. We're
We're good. Let's actually put it on the
tip. Look at that. We're Whoop. So that
sensing is uh
The sensor's not terrific, is it? Is it
genuinely actually going down to 85°
C?
But if it is, look at how quickly it
recovers, right? Bang. It's It's already
back. It overshot to 280, but it's back,
you know, up, ready to do the next
joint. And that's the advantage of these
things. These things are
uh very powerful
in that respect in that you can do lots
of joints very quickly. If you want to
do a joint every second or two,
you probably should have one of these.
This may not cut it if you do that. So
that temperature drop can be a real big
deal. It can make or break a A, what
temperature you solder at, and B, what
types of devices you're able to solder.
If you're looking at a reasonably, you
know, a large copper ground plane like
this, it's going to absorb or sink more
heat from the tip of the soldering iron
uh than a soldering a little, you know,
0603 surface mount component with a tiny
little pad. Or if you're soldering the
big tab of a big power transistor or
something, that will act as a big heat
sink. And this also has to do with uh
the temperature melting point
temperature of your solder. And we won't
go into the uh metallurgical stuff of
that. That's a whole field in its own
thing in the plastic region. And you've
got to understand all sorts of things.
But suffice it to say that your lead
free
uh solder that um that you know
you're supposed to use these days has a
higher melting point temperature of two
it varies depending on the
type, but this type by 99C here um melts
at a nominal 227°
C
and your good old
uh lead solder like your good old 60/40
or you you know 63/37 or you you know
like the 70 bit ones like this. These
will melt at 183°
C. So, you know, there's a a good what
uh 45 odd degrees difference between
these two and when you when you're
soldering your joint you've got to
factor into account that temperature
drop of your tip. So, let's actually
just experiment with a couple of these
different types and I'll show you.
So, what we're going to try and do is
solder onto a ground plane like this.
It's not the biggest ground plane in the
world, but it's a ground plane using uh
lead free solder that melts at a nominal
227°
C and we'll set both of our irons to
240°.
So, above that, so we should find that
it'll actually melt. And now I'll put
some
flux on there just so it activates and
let's have a look at our old school
iron. Here we go.
It should the
the solder
it's actually it it will melt. There you
go. It will melt cuz it's reached that
but let's see
if it'll actually do that
down on the board, shall we?
Here we go.
No.
No, it's not it's not working well. No,
it's like uh stone motherless cold.
Look, I mean it's just Look at that.
Hopeless, right? It's kind of sort of
just stuck there. But let's do the exact
same thing
with 240° on the JBC here. So, let's
give this a whirl. One side of this tip
is a bit
bit crusty. So, let's try the JBC, shall
we?
Let's see if it can do it at 240°C.
Yep, it can do it just. It It's melting
it. Yeah, it it it did the job. There
you go. So, that is the difference there
between these two. With the direct heat
iron, we can
solder lead-free onto a ground plane at
you know, 240°C. We can go down a bit.
We could drop it down to 220°C and it's
just not going to work at all. But, we
can go to a really low safe temperature.
And that's the goal of almost any
soldering is to use the lowest
temperature you can that's going to do
the job properly and do it in a timely
manner, of course. It It's no point uh
going so low a temperature that you have
to leave the iron there forever until it
actually
you know, melts up cuz
that could leaving it longer there could
heat up the component more and stress
it. So, it's a bit of a trade-off, but
in generally speaking, you want to do it
at the lowest temperature you can that
gets the job done quickly enough. And in
this case,
this one, the direct heat iron, wins.
Okay, let's uh let's try the Hakko at
260°C,
shall we?
Let's give that a whirl.
And see if we can get it to
heat up. Come on.
You can do it.
No, doesn't like it. Okay, let's try it
at 270°C, shall we?
Okay, let's try it
on a new section here
complete with the flux
at 270°C and
No.
No, still can't do it. And if we try it
at 280,
I can actually get it to do the
business. But once again, remember this
is a less powerful iron. 65 watts versus
a 130 watts peak there. But you know, I
I was able to get it at a lower
temperature, but
yeah, it's kind of sort of a bit hit and
miss. You have to leave it there for a
while, but you can see the difference.
Just in case you're curious, no, the
Weller can't do it at 240 either.
Hopeless. And 260 with the Weller, yeah,
it's struggling. The solder's melting,
but uh jeez, it's not that great. And
once again, you just get the uh JBC
on there and at uh at nominal 240,
no problems whatsoever. Look at that.
But it's a different ball game if we
want to use uh 60/40 solder that melts
at 183°C.
I've got all four irons set to uh 240
volts uh set temperature here. And let's
try the Hakko. This has already got some
over here. And
bingo. Look at that. 240
Oh.
Takes a second or two to get the heat
into it, but no problems whatsoever,
right? And we can do the same thing with
the Weller here. 240. Haven't tried the
Weller yet.
But
there we go.
It can do a similar thing. So, they can
all melt. And of course, the JBC is
going to
I'm choking on the fumes. JBC's going to
do the business. But as you can see,
it's kind of like a much quicker
application there. Like um if I go like
that, boom. That was with no flux. Let's
try this with the Hakko with no flux,
shall we?
It It's Oh, it's almost as good. But but
you can feel it stick a little bit more.
But there's not much in that. Both can
like all of them can use a low
temperature of 240° C with 60/40 solder
onto a ground plane like that. You know,
yeah, you can tell the JBC's ahead, but
not as much as it is with the uh
lead-free solder. All right, so let's
actually have some fun with the Flir ETS
320 thermal camera which can go up to
260° C. So I'll use uh lead leaded
solder um and we'll use the 240°
temperature we had before and we'll
check out the uh how it looks under the
thermal camera see if we can see the
temperature drop. All right, so let's do
this. I'm going to use the uh Hakko
first and I haven't tried this yet. So
let's actually I've got what I've got is
the center point. This is the point I'm
going to solder. So that's going to be
I'll put that like smack in the middle
like that so we can read the temperature
up there, but also the max it should
tell us the maximum soldering iron
temperature up there. So let's do a
test. Okay, so what we need to do is I
actually set up the emissivity and
there's a whole list of uh custom
materials and stuff in here and really
like you know there's copper polished
and all that sort of jazz, but um yeah,
really we're we're just going to have to
do this by experimentation by setting
the custom value like this. I've already
set it to 0.5. It was a bit over. So I'm
going to set it to uh 0.4 and we'll give
that a whirl.
And cuz we know our temperature of our
iron's pretty accurate cuz we measured
it the other time 240. Uh I'll tweak it
a bit more, but uh yeah, we'll we'll get
it right. Okay, I'm going to call that
um at 0.35 emissivity 246. Doesn't
matter, right? We can actually what we
want to do is we want to see the
temperature drop. So, we're looking in
the top uh right
corner of that and see the temperature
drop. So, let's try the Hakko
at
There we go. So, it was 240. Let's see
what happens when we actually heat up
our big copper here.
There we go. It's dropping by
Once again, it's the It's the Well, the
top side of the tip, I guess you could
say. So,
it's uh
What?
You get What is it doing? It's barely
doing it. It was doing it well before.
There we go. There we go. See, so it
hasn't dropped by a huge amount. It's
dropping maybe 215 or something.
Like that. It hasn't
It's not dropping by a huge amount on
this particular type of copper clad.
But, let's see how the JBC holds up to
that, shall we?
Wow. Okay, it looks like we've got
a very different emissivity for our
JBC here. So, I I may have to
I may have to tweak it
yet again. It really, you know, it's
It's a big difference there. Quite
surprised by that. But, anyway, let's
let's tweak it again. All right, we'll
run with that. I've got an emissivity of
0.75.
So, let's do the
JBC here.
You can see that yeah, it it really
doesn't drop
by anything. It can But, once again,
this is 135 W peak. Just remember that.
So, that could be all the difference in
this particular case. But, as you can
see, it did that with basically
very Well, I get maybe Okay, let's just
say 10° C drop or something like that.
But, you can you get the idea that the
direct irons like these direct heat
irons are obviously going to have a
better thermal capacity than your old
style ones. So, let's actually just turn
the heat up to 270, which is 30° higher
than the JBC, but in terms of actually
doing a ground plane like this, but in
terms of actually damage a component,
it's going to basically drop down to the
same
temperature anyway. So, you know, it's
not really a problem. And there it is,
you know, it
it's a little bit struggling a little
bit, but once again, you know, you could
turn it up, but there you go. Like it's
it's melting just fine. But of course,
the JBC, of course, will just do that
like straight on. I don't even need to
add in like straight on
at
240. So, you know, there you go. But at
the end of the day, that copper's
probably at you know, a similar sort of
temperature. Yeah, it's better, but it's
not a huge
deal, really. It still works. It gets
the job done. You might have to turn the
heat up a little bit, but
it's not enough to damage your
components. And for low thermal mass
components,
there's going to be practically no
difference between these, really. If
you're doing surface mount
soldering or anything like that, there's
just like this one's just going to do as
good a job as this one. It's only when
you get into a higher thermal mass
component, and really now, if you're
doing a joint per second or something
like that, it could make a difference,
but overall,
it's a huge amount for just general
purpose soldering. So, there you go. I
hope you found that interesting look at
a old technology
indirect heat one and a new modern
direct drive one. And I completely agree
with Louis. These are better. There's
absolutely no doubt about that. But
these are not I don't necessarily agree
that these are, you know, crap or you
shouldn't buy them. I think, you know,
for 100 bucks okay, you can argue like
Lewis um said that
a $100 you can buy a rip-off
direct drive one, a rip-off Hakko direct
drive one from the Shenzhen market and
it's crap quality inside, but he reckons
I haven't tested one, but he reckons
that um it works almost as good as the
uh direct drive Hakko FX-951
or you can spend 100 bucks on the FX-888
this older style one, but they work
okay. Yeah, you're not going to be do
doing high volume production soldering.
If you're there just, you know, like
boing boing boing, you know, like an
extra second or two it takes to heat up
to reheat this compared to this. If you
have a look at that Hakko uh graph
again, then yeah, you know, it
you have to let it if you did uh 2
seconds per joint, then this one's going
to do the job and this one just may not
work at all. If you want 2 seconds per
joint, depending on once again the type
of solder that you use, the thermal
capacity uh the thermal sink capacity of
the device you're trying to the pad
you're uh component you're trying to
heat up and all that sort of jazz.
There's lots of things that go into it,
but yeah, if you're doing high-speed
soldering or maybe big ground planes
like Lewis is doing with repairs and uh
stuff like that on big modern uh
motherboards and stuff like that. Yeah,
definitely get one of these, but these
are not as crappy as you might think.
You can do an awful lot with these if
not
most things that you're, you know,
regular hobbyist or enthusiast is going
to encounter. So, there's nothing wrong
with these at all.
I hope you found that interesting. If
you did, please give it a big thumbs up
and as always discuss it down below and
I'm sure everyone will. And yes, I um
plan on getting uh Pace have got a new
uh the ADS200
direct drive um iron that they're uh
sending me and I'll probably get an FX
Hakko FX-951 to compare that with and
everything else. I might do a shootout
of
direct drive irons. I Is that the
correct term? Direct heating, direct
drive, I integrated tip, whatever you
want to call it. Anyway, it's
interesting, but there's a lot of
variables
that go into this. As I said, the type
of solder and the patch you're using and
the
temperature you want to solder at, the
recovery time that you want, the number
of joints per second that you want to
do, the maximum temperature of the
component that you're looking at, the,
not only the maximum temperature of the
component, but the amount of time you
can leave that heat on there and
there's just countless things. If you
really want to go down the rabbit hole,
you can. But, yeah, if you can afford
it, get one of these direct drive ones.
Anyway,
hope you found it interesting. Catch you
next time.